Today, I sat down with Bernardo Bilota, founder of Stable's Money.
Stable allows users globally to save and spend money in stablecoins with a focus on Asia-Pacific regions.
Bernardo started Stable's in early 2021, back when the total supply of stablecoins was only about $50 billion,
a mere 20% of today's $250 billion total supply.
He and the team built and launched the application with the goal of offering a dollar savings account
to those who may be seeking alternatives to savings exclusively in their local currency,
a theme we've discussed often on this podcast.
And this at a time when stablecoin adoption was in its relative infancy and future use cases were somewhat unclear.
Stable's has found an audience and more.
In the process of growing a retail user base, users also started to ask Stable's if they could help them with their business needs.
Today, Stable's continues to grow and services retail users and businesses alike
when it comes to saving and spending in stablecoins with an everlasting focus on the Asia-Pacific region
and meaningful penetration in those markets to date.
I think quite highly of Bernardo and the business that he and the team have built.
But beyond that, I was keen to have him join us as I believe that while we hear a lot about stablecoin adoption across the globe,
it is insightful to hear these direct accounts from relevant industry leaders,
particularly when it comes to regional activity that we may not see up close as often, if at all.
Without further ado, I hope you enjoy my conversation with Bernardo.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep!
The federal government is stepping it to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac,
the two mortgage giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more to Britain's ailing economy with a new round of quantitative easing.
They've printed a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin. Bitcoin.
Bernie, thanks for coming on.
Who uses stables? Who does it serve today? Who's your audience?
Stables really serves, I'd say, predominantly two different types of user demographic.
Firstly, individuals. You can think of them as crypto-native.
So people that already have stablecoins understand the benefit of all these stablecoins
and using them on-chain. And they want to kind of utilize them to the real world.
And crypto-agnostic, so people that they have come about stablecoins out of necessity
rather than by being constantly, chronically online.
And also we're servicing businesses.
On the business vertical, it's almost something that we stumble on by mistake.
We originally started as a consumer product.
And I think it's actually a violation when you see people misusing your product
in a way that you would be like, hey, I don't fully understand what's going on there.
So you go and talk to these people and it turns out there were businesses.
Yeah, it's unexpected product market fit.
Right. People or individuals in businesses, they go through unnecessary pain to go and solve a problem.
We go and talk to these folks and they're like, hey, we actually have business
and we're utilizing the platform for these use cases.
And what it really transpires there, it's almost like there is a platform arbitration
rather than regulatory and compliance arbitration, which basically means that these people realize
the stablecoins are way better to go and run their business operation on transaction.
And they just need a platform that allows them to go from stablecoin into local currency
in one floor rather than go and stitch it up altogether across different five, six different providers.
Those are the, say, like high level at the two demographics.
Going forward, one that I'm quite excited about is the developer demographic.
We started with individual then started servicing businesses.
The other thing that we kind of stumble across, probably like, you know, by mistake again,
it's people that want to have access to our rails, you know, one single easy integration.
And these people are either developer businesses or almost like foundation
that they really want access to stablecoins in a way that fits their use cases and purposes.
Where are these consumers and businesses?
Where are they in the world and what do they do generally?
Why would build stable to be like a very global product?
Inherently, we have these believe stablecoins are a global product
and so you need to be able to service the global audience through the call
and discover you by mistake.
However, our vertical and kind of very expertise is really around Asia and Mina.
That's where we see the majority of our flaws originating from and going into
and as well, like, you know, a majority of signups.
And I would say strategically also those jurisdiction, at least to me, are way more interesting
than, you know, other jurisdiction that like kind of far away and detached from us
in a wheelbase across Australia and the broader Asia region.
I think it's like there's a big opportunity there for stablecoin to kind of go
and create some connectivity tissue in otherwise very fragmented market.
There's a lot of different currency, a lot of different use cases
and almost country in quite a large, you know, geographical area.
However, there's a lot of trade remittances and money movement across all of these geographies.
And what you're noticing is like there's a lot of usually like intermediary banking
to go from, you know, one place to another, even though somewhat closely located,
then it takes a lot of time and effort to get money from point A to point B.
We really believe that, like, you know, almost why stablecoin
have really took heat escape velocity in Africa, Latin, Coliseum de Moa, developed war.
There is a big use cases in, you know, going to serve like fragmented and large markets such as Asia.
A relatively spread out user base, it sounds like, in certain pockets of Asia.
How are users finding you and what's the scope of how many people you have on the platform
and how much money moves today?
That is actually like one of the questions that I always tried to answer myself
because we never done any marketing or incentives for Dan Mera.
Today, like, it's just through organic discovery and kind of word of mouth.
I think it's like it does help when you do have a beautiful product to get discovered that way.
People are way more prone to go and say, hey, you should go and try that product this week.
For instance, I think the other day, somebody from the, I think Austin Federa from Kev Solana Foundation
was talking about, like, somebody needs to go and build a product
that allows people to go and issue local beans.
And the, like, a gazillion people are just tagging us.
It's not like we were there actively.
And so, like, I think that's like, it's almost like, you know, when you have a good product
that actually go and solve a pain point for a specific demographic,
then, like, that's how you get this kind of, like, growth loop of people just, like, go and say,
you should go and try this product this week and work.
In terms of how much money we're moving, it's been about, say, 15 months that we are in market showing numbers.
Today, we process about $300 million in TPV through our rails.
That's annualized?
That is over 50 months.
Like, now we're averaging, I'll say, monthly about 12 to 25 million.
I'm expecting to annex that over the next three to six months
as we, you know, building more specific features like some of our customers
that want to come on board and, you know, move larger volume are requesting us.
And so, it's like, really, I think, like, the philosophy of building products, at least for us,
we do believe we're a product-led growth company,
is we build something that we believe we're solving a problem.
Like, we, of course, talk to customer and talk to people
and understand what sort of problem he was solving.
And then, by doing that, you know, as I mentioned, incidentally,
we're solving other problems for other people in demographics.
Now, we're just talking to this new demographic that we're going to found into a better understanding.
What do we need to do in order for you to go and move all your volume over to us?
I think, like, once you go and craft that,
that's where things are going to get very, very interesting
because, like, the volume are considerably higher.
I like how you describe it as growth loops
because you have this effect that we've seen in stablecoins, at least,
where you have stakeholders in the tether network.
They want to grow tether, which, in turn, helps stables grow.
You have people who are growing binance, which, in turn,
might lead users to then find out about stables.
So you have these parallel growth narratives.
I wanted to ask on a couple of points you mentioned.
What's a typical transaction size?
And what is a typical transaction insofar as are people sending money to each other in Venmo style?
Are they paying for things?
Or what is a typical transaction behaviorally as well?
So with stables, most of these three types of transaction that we can do it,
at least the way that we talk about it, is you can top up your account.
That could be, you know, stablecoin transaction,
or it could be, like, a purchase of you depositing local currency
through virtual bank accounts or a bank card to purchase stablecoins.
It could be a send transaction.
So it's almost like going from the platform out
and this could be eating stablecoins or local currencies.
And then it could be a spending transaction.
So we have a stablecoin account that connects to a stablecoin balance.
So on the top up or purchase transaction average,
or the size that we're seeing at the moment, it's about 2.1K.
So relatively large?
Yeah, it's quite large.
It gets queued up because there'd be people that do, like, big transaction,
and people that do very small transactions.
So it kind of ends up there in the middle.
On the send, it's about kind of similar.
I'll say, like, a little higher, like 3.4K.
And that's usually what you see is, like, most of the time,
it's people sending into local currencies.
And then on the card size,
we're seeing about $70 per transaction average or the size.
What's interesting there is we do see increasingly
the amount of spending being completed on everyday purchases.
So that, at least to me, is an indication
of people utilizing stables more and more for their everyday
and becoming their everyday digital US dollar account,
which I think is, like, it could unlock a bunch of very interesting stuff
down the road.
But it's all, like, very encouraging,
especially on the frequency of how often this transaction,
like, all of these customers that transact,
usually they are a repeat transactor.
And the interesting side is that once you manage to give somebody a card,
they're becoming a much better user than a user that doesn't have a card.
I remember seeing that also back in the fintech days,
once you manage to get a person to utilize their phone and give them a card,
their LTV grows exponentially.
They can use it daily at that point.
They don't need to rely on joint financial products.
Right.
How do total deposits compare to volume?
Do people keep a lot of money on the platform as well
that they're not immediately using for payments?
Not really, because at the moment,
the platform is really optimized for velocity of money,
rather than, like, kind of money sink.
And it's also, like, no reason for them to hold the balance with us
other than spending or on rent and off rent.
Just because, like, at the moment, there's no yield component
or any sort of incentives for you to hold the balance there,
which is a great opportunity there to go and do something about it.
I think it's like, you can go and start gamifying even further.
Like, wouldn't it be cool if you have a magic balance that goes up
in real time that you can spend, buy stuff from or remit from?
It's like that big kind of UX unlock that, I think,
only programmable money really allows you to go and do.
And it actually happens, rather than, like, you know,
numbering a database kind of thing now.
So I think there's, like, a lot of stuff there that, like,
it's yet to either play out and, you know, big opportunity
on optimizing them almost like for deposit size versus velocity amount.
It's interesting that, especially given the parts of the world
that you guys serve, that this more of a spending-friendly product
already has that level of traction,
because I would imagine if anything,
the main demand would be to store money and maybe earn yield in dollars
as opposed to for the spend aspect.
If I was to listen to my customer, I would already have yielded out.
It's one of those, like, more requested feature.
We did explore it for a while.
That's how we actually originally started.
But at the time, I think, like, now there's a lot more regulatory clarity there.
Given, like, Auntie, more recently,
it was seen as a very risky and kind of gray area
to go and offer yield on customers' deposit.
Like, you see other people that just say, earn reward.
Like, there's, like, other structure that you could go and do without passing through yield.
But, yeah, definitely, that's one of the things that customers want.
They want to have the ability to just, like, store stable coins,
see number goes up, spend from that balance without having to go to different platforms.
That being said, I think it's like,
this is just an indication almost like how stable coins are, in fact,
a superior form of money for payments more broadly.
These people come to us because they either go,
the financial system kind of failed them,
they don't serve because they consider it to be either high-risk clients
or it's hard for them to go and stitch all these different payment methods together.
While I do want to do a yield, I also think payment itself is, like,
big enough for the vertical to just go and bid all business on it.
It's telling also the transaction size, like you mentioned,
that these are a couple thousand dollar transactions right now.
It's clear that for meaningful movements of money, people are preferring this system.
If someone makes a card payment using stables,
how does it settle?
Presumably, that'll be two merchants in a variety of countries, right?
Yeah, so the way that it works is we do this process called Adjusting Time Funding.
So, effectively, the difference is from at least the traditional concept of having a card balance.
Back in the day, you have a card, you got to move money onto the card.
The card becomes a value store card and then you got to spend all the money on the card.
And usually, it wasn't possible to go and take them out.
So, like, the only way was, like, to spend it all.
It's like Starbucks.
Right, yeah, yeah. And while it's functional, it's not ideal.
Also because, like, I think, like, back in the days,
there were a lot of these crypto cards that they were, like, using this model
and then they, like, disappear overnight.
It happened to me once.
Yours went away?
No, they don't run away.
Well, pretty much because they're basically doing things they're not supposed to.
Or, like, back in the day, card issuer weren't as friendly towards, you know, crypto more broadly.
And so, like, these people were actually saying,
we're doing something completely different.
And then once they get caught by the scheme, they get cut off.
But, like, what happened is, like, you have the money on the card, the money's gone.
And so, it's like, ideally, the way that these things work is really, like, do things properly
so that that doesn't happen to your customer.
Number one, number two is, like, Adjusting Time Funding cards.
You don't actually need to store.
User balances on a card.
You can just use Delegate a Loaf model to basically go and say,
when you go to a store and you tap at a post,
what's happening is there's a thing that goes from the post to our backend to check,
hey, do you have enough money for this transaction size?
If you do, return it to Android, return, clear the transaction.
And then, at the end of the day, when the merchant goes and captures the transaction,
we would do all the on-chain settlement.
So, you say it's a $5 transaction for a coffee.
The merchant, at the end of the day, goes and captures the transaction.
There's $5 on-chain that moves to, like, a float account, a settlement account.
And then, from the settlement account, we offer MP and we do the settlement
and, you know, with the merchants directly.
And, you know, that happens on a number of currency, of course.
People travel and do a bunch of stuff in the day-to-day life.
With the scheme, like, we just need to settle with the scheme.
Usually, that's how it works.
So, the cashier, we just send the money into local currency
and then they take care of the merchants.
Yeah, it seems like an attractive product,
especially if you're a digital nomad-type remote worker
and you just want to have an account denominated in dollars
where you can use in any country or place that you go to.
A hundred percent. I mean, I don't know if you ever had a pleasure
or try opening up a brokerage account, like, when you try and get, like, T-bills
or, you know, access to the dollar.
So, some people is actually not that hard,
but then giving certain jurisdiction is actually quite impossible.
It's either, like, capital control that don't allow you to do it
or the amount of documentation that you require
just to, like, even buy one single dollar is staggering.
This onboarding form that's just coming straight out of the settlement
takes you, like, six hours to complete it
and maybe you get it done in...
In a month's time, you're onboarded
versus just streamlining completely in a mobile-first experience
that you just go,
let's go and see you.
Let's make sure that we have enough details
about who's actually initiating these transactions.
We make access to dollar simple and easy and fast.
Like, you should be able to go and buy your first dollar,
spend your dollar or, like, you know, send money in three minutes,
type of things. Like, those are the benchmark.
Rather than go and say, yeah, you will get back to you in six weeks.
It's a big unlock when it comes to almost, like, the zero-to-one moment,
like, what stablecoin really unlock is that magic moment of,
hold on a second, I can go and access dollar in under three minutes
versus legacy system that either prevent me completely from accessing this dollar
or they're just, like, putting all this red tape around me
being able to access this dollar
and so, like, you know, making everything slower and more cumbersome.
We've talked a lot about your offering.
Why did you guys choose to call it stables?
I think you hear maybe the word dollar or send a lot
and names of companies operating in this space.
Why did you go after the namesake stables?
It's actually a bit of a funny story.
Stables is a rebrand from our originally previous name that we had.
It's called TEEK, TEEKEEPLIK.
At the time, stablecoins weren't that in general and we were like,
because really the way that we see it is there is a problem to be solved
because for crypto natives that such as ourselves,
they have digital dollar, but it's actually hard to go and use this digital dollar
in the real world and then there is the next iteration of the product.
It's like, go and get the normies to utilize all these special rails,
magic internet money rails.
And so stables is really, it's the jargon for stablecoins in their industry.
But it's also like, I think there's a funny comparison
that is also a place where the horses stay.
So like the way that we're thinking about it was,
we're going to have a stables of product.
We thought it was funny.
Yeah, it's a stable for stables.
Right. But it's a great asset because now stablecoins are hot
and we are stables money.
It's our own trademark.
Maybe that's a valuable on his own, I suppose.
That's probably a valuable domain too, I figure.
Right, yeah.
And at the time, it wasn't very hot.
We got a good deal on it and let's put it that way.
When people talk about your guys platform,
do they describe it as a neobank or a savings product?
Because a stablecoin account isn't something that I imagine.
Like you said, you have this viral effect.
I wouldn't think people are describing it that way.
I have a mixed feeling at times about the word neobank
because we should be calling things for what they are.
But we're definitely not a bank.
But that is also like the things that people resonate, I'll say the most.
It's like, oh, it's a neobank.
I can buy things.
I can store things.
I can spend from it.
Familiar with Revolut or The Wise,
that's how they probably like to categorize it.
But I think it's more about payments.
The way that people talk about stable is more like a payment platform.
Like you can load it up with stablecoins
and you can give your stablecoins real utility.
I think it's probably going to become a cause on your bank.
Once you're able to go and offer like a more about earned saving offering
because then you have payments,
you have money saving, you have broad opportunities.
But yeah, I think it's at the moment,
it's more on the payment angle side of things.
I want an offer.
I think that's how people really, especially in this industry,
that's how people see it.
As much as we believe stablecoins are new,
I think there's actually way more understood that,
especially I think like in the deeper South,
way more understood than us in the West,
just because we don't need to use them necessarily, right?
And people do understand the stablecoins are for payments.
And people understand like what a stablecoin is
and what are the benefits of stablecoins.
And so once you have a stablecoins,
you can do one or two things, right?
Like you eat it all day or you own an off-ramp.
And so I think that's the easiest way to think about it.
You go from magic internal money to come in real-world money
and do stuff with it.
At the moment, that's how it is in my change, was it?
How do banks behave towards you guys?
Do they want to work with you?
Do they not like you?
What's their sentiment?
It's been four years that we've been swimming against the current,
I would say.
I think this is evolving especially now with the progress
and changes in administrations
and almost perspective towards what stablecoins are going to enable.
It was really hard.
It's still very hard.
One of the things that are actually very hard in this space,
which is basically I think the only thing that's actually worthwhile doing,
by the way, everything else will eventually get commoditized.
If it hasn't been already commoditized,
getting the banking rail and working with the bank is one of the two things.
If you do things properly,
if you have proper compliance framework, KOSC, AML,
totally like global program,
then now banks are way more open and receptive to go and work.
With stablecoin provided, like to give you an example,
four years ago,
we started working one of the largest payment processors in Southeast Asia.
We started as a pilot in only one country in the Philippines,
and it took us four years to get to the point
that now they want to go and open up all of the rail to us,
which is going to be highly significant.
It takes time and it takes a lot of work to get where you at
because they need to get comfortable with you.
They need to see that you have the right processes,
then framework in place.
They need to see that you lost the test of time.
They actually run a real business.
They are handling compliance and all of those processes are properly,
and then you have the right people to go and operate the licenses.
Usually, they just want to work with license businesses,
which we are in a number of jurisdictions.
That kind of gives you, I think,
now a structural advantage versus just go and utilize somebody else's infrastructure.
The way I see it, it's going to be almost...
You have a million customers and you can distribute to this customer very quickly.
I think user experience plays a big role in that.
Or you actually own the licenses and the infrastructure
that you can allow and enable other people to go and build experiences on it.
I think that something that has always been very misunderstood about Stables
is that we do both.
While we play at the app layer,
we also have all the licenses to go and do all the info play that we want to write.
And so now, because we've been in market for so long,
because we've got traction, now this conversation is becoming a whole lot more streamlined,
interesting and almost fruitful.
Because now these people that come and talk to us
because they want to get the food into stable coins,
they want to get stable coins flowing into the platform.
A company that probably back in the days,
even a couple of years ago, didn't fully understand the space.
Now they understand that not playing in the space is going to...
There's an opportunity cost there.
And so they just want to go and play with people that...
They license, they've done it for a while,
and they write people on the team to go and serve the status laws and use cases, of course.
It's never easy.
They're late to the game, but you start to realize
the cost of not participating is higher than the cost
they've had perceived of participating before.
You touched on compliance.
The primary criticism that I hear for an app like this, let's say,
is a user on board's funds, they convert the stable coins,
they send it to a wallet.
How do you know that wallet isn't in North Korea
or that transaction is illicit or used for money laundering?
What's your response and how do you guys look at compliance
and avoiding potential illicit activity on the platform?
Maybe the good preamble here is the other non-consensus things
that we've done back in the day.
And aside from getting excited about stable coins
when nobody was excited about stable coins, it was IK.
These stable coins are going to become the future of money
and there are actually better for our money
the way that we understand it.
However, because it's money nonetheless,
you need to approach it like a fully already regulated
financial product.
And at the time, it was kind of on the outskirt of,
it's still unsure what this is.
And we always approach it like a fully regulated financial product.
So we got financial licenses to go and structure
regulated financial product.
We literally structure a fully regulated and compliant
remittance product powered by stable coins.
Some of these product, the structure across Australia,
Europe, Canada, and soon UAE.
And in some of these countries such as Australia,
like the regulator pride themselves to be one of the
toughest regulator in the world
when it comes to financial services.
And so for us, the fact that we've been able to come
to structure product that clears Australia standards,
basically mean that we can then go and scale this globally
because the Commonwealth is like,
while not the same everywhere,
it's like quite shared across the major economies.
So if you can go and cover it there,
then you can go and export it elsewhere,
which is like, you know, what happened with us?
In terms of how do we approach collect risk and compliance
and more broadly like customer onboarding?
When you come to the platform,
you can decide to sign up here as individual as a business.
We can we see you or can we be you?
And that basically means selfies, proof of address,
you be all directors, shoulders, whatever you name it.
So once you have an account, I mean, it just doesn't stops there.
Compliance, it's one of those things.
So like, you know, as a founder, you go and say,
it's painful because it costs a lot of money,
but then it's really one of the few assets,
you know, going back to licensing that you really have a hand.
And if you do it properly,
that's what makes the business valuable
because you can go and grow very quickly
by kind of turning a blind eye to compliance,
but then that actually the value of your business law,
especially as we become more and more institutionalized,
people value the fact that you're running things properly
without compromising there.
The things that we do is, you know,
we build our own proprietary fraud and risk engine
where we're feeding a bunch of data that we have on our customers
to making sure of we have identified certain risky patterns
that, you know, we know they usually led to fraud.
And so that would kind of flag certain activities.
We're also using, like, you know, transaction monitoring tool.
We're also using KYT tools to the point that, like, you know,
we know that you don't send money to a North Korean wallet.
These things, by the way, it's a never-ending battle.
Every time that we usually launch a new product,
the way that it works is like, you have all this control,
you launch a new product,
and then what happens is you realize there was an area
that you were exposed.
Somebody comes and kind of exploit it,
and then you go and say, cool, now I got the data
to go and make my system stronger.
Over time, that's how you build battle-tested systems
because, you know, similar infintech is the same.
Fraud serves very smart.
Getting better.
They're always changing the system.
They always adapt into the new meta and the new tooling.
And so, like, you always need to be up to scratch with that.
Otherwise, they're always going to find a way
to go and exploit loopholes, platforms, and whatever.
Right now, the way that we see working is, you know,
like KYC, transaction monitoring, KYT,
and then, like, you know, our own proprietary fraud
and risk engine where all the data effectively get fed into.
And then, like, there's, like, almost a decision engine
that, like, based on all of these data points,
then we're able to go and make decisions in real time.
This is a piece of the puzzle
that people talk about publicly a lot.
But for you guys internally,
what are the risks or the single risks
that you keep in mind, mostly,
as being paramount to the business
and that you do most of your work to try and mitigate or avoid?
First of all, it would be we need to make sure
that we know what our customers are.
Our biggest risk, single-handedly, is KML and KYC.
And, again, like, while it adds to your business value
if you do properly,
it's highly deterring if you don't do it properly, right?
Like, if you let that actor through your platform,
then that's how the business goes to zero.
You get fine.
Literally, you go and destroy all the things
that you built from that.
So, like, I think for us,
that is the main risk and concerns.
It's, like, making sure that we're abiding to AML and KYC.
Rules and laws.
We have a full-time chief risk officer
and general counsel on the team
that usually you don't get to see,
like, in many early days, startups.
But that's because we understand, like, you know,
we're dealing with people's money.
And so it becomes paramount
to make sure that you don't screw it up there.
The other thing is security, more broadly.
We want to make sure that we have all the right controls
for to prevent account takeover,
to prevent loss of funds,
and whatnot so, like, you know, we have implemented
through a phase, the device, the intelligence,
there is, you know, biometrics.
There's a bunch of smarts that,
when you're using the product,
you might not necessarily appreciate
that it takes a long time to go and build.
But, like, those are the things that are actually important
when you go and build consumer purchasing products
because if your customer comes and uses the app
and then somehow somebody is able to come
and enter into the account and drain your funds,
then it's never good.
It's almost like those two things,
at least they keep me up at night,
making sure that the money is where it's supposed to be,
and making sure that nobody
that is not supposed to go and touch the money,
touches it.
I think good pieces to keep in mind
for anyone building a product in this general area
is, I'm sure we'll see many of them.
Yeah, don't screw that up.
Bernie, thank you for joining.
I really enjoyed the conversation
and I'm sure we'll chat again soon.
Sounds like a plan.
It was a pleasure being here.
Go Stables.
Yeah, thanks, Ben.
See you later.
Thanks for listening to another episode
of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island,
visit castleisland.vc.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com
or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.